<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!-- This document was created with Syntext Serna Free. --><chapter id="ch1_general_info" lang="en">
  <title>FTS Subsystem Overview</title>
  <para>Full-text search (FTS) capabilities of the CUBA platform provide unstructured search within the values of entity attributes and content of uploaded files.</para>
  <para>A distinctive aspect of full-text search implementation in CUBA is its focus on business applications with complex data models. Particularly, search results include not only the entities that directly contain the search string but also the related entities which use this attribute when being displayed. For example, if an  <code>Order</code> entity contains a link to a  <code>Customer</code> and the search string contains the name of the customer, then search results will include both the  <code>Customer</code> and the related <code>Order</code>. This behavior is logical for a user who typically sees the name of the customer in the order editing screen.</para>
  <para>Search results are filtered according to the limitations applied by the platform’s security subsystem. I.e. if the current user’s access group does not allow access to certain entity instances, such instances will not appear in search results.</para>
  <para>Full-text search subsystem contains two mutually related mechanisms: indexing and search.</para>
  <section>
    <title>Indexing</title>
    <para>If the FTS base project is included as base project in the application, and the  <property>
        <link linkend="cuba.fts.enabled">cuba.fts.enabled</link>
      </property> property is enabled, then each time when an indexable entity is being saved to the database its identifier gets added to the indexing queue -  <database>SYS_FTS_QUEUE</database> table.</para>
    <para>A separate asynchronous process periodically extracts identifiers of changed entities from the queue, loads entity instances and indexes them. Indexing is performed using the   <application>Apache Lucene</application> library. Lucene document contains the following fields:  <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Entity name and instance identifier.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para><code>all</code> – concatenation of the entity attributes being indexed, which includes only local and   <code>FileDescriptor</code> type attributes. If the attribute has  <code>FileDescriptor</code> type, the system will index the content of the corresponding file. Local attributes may have the following type: string, number, date, enumeration.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para><code>links</code>  – concatenation of entities  identifiers contained in indexed attributes having reference type.  </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist></para>
    <para>Indexed attributes are the attributes of the entity and related entities (if any), which are declared in the FTS descriptor.</para>
    <para>Index is stored in the file system; by default it is located in the   <filename>ftsindex</filename> subfolder of the application work folder (defined by the  <property>cuba.dataDir</property> property); for a standard deployment this folder is <filename>tomcat/work/app-core/ftsindex</filename>. Index location can be changed using the   <link linkend="cuba.fts.indexDir">cuba.fts.indexDir</link> property.</para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Searching</title>
    <para>Search is performed according to the following rules: <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>If the search term is included in quotation marks, the system searches for the corresponding  <emphasis role="bold">phrase</emphasis> – the same set of words in the same order ignoring the punctuation.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>If the search term begins with &quot;*&quot;, the system searches for the term as a substring  <emphasis role="bold">in any part of a word</emphasis> in indexed data.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Otherwise search is performed by matching the search term with the   <emphasis role="bold">beginnings of the words </emphasis> in indexed data.  </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist></para>
    <para>For Russian and English languages search accounts for word forms.</para>
    <para>Search algorithm contains two stages:  <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>First, the search term is looked for in the <code>all</code> field of Lucene documents. All found entities are added to the results list.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>If the first stage produces results, the identifiers of found entities are then searched in the  <code>links</code> field of Lucene documents. All entities found at the second stage are also added to the list of search results.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist></para>
    <warning>
      <para>If the search string contains several words (not enclosed in quotation marks) the system will search each word separately using OR condition. I.e. search results will include the entities containing at least one of the entered words.</para>
    </warning>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title lang="en">Indexing and Searching Example </title>
    <para>Let us consider the simple case of linked   <code>Order</code> and  <code>Customer</code> entities mentioned above.  <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="img/Example1Classes.png" align="center"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject></para>
    <para>In this case, if all object attributes are indexed, indexing of two related instances of   <code>Order</code> and  <code>Customer</code> will create two Lucene documents with approximately the following content:</para>
    <programlisting>id: Order.id = &quot;b671dbfc-c431-4586-adcc-fe8b84ca9617&quot;
all: Order.number + Order.date + Order.amount = &quot;001^2013-11-14^1000&quot;
links: Customer.id = &quot;f18e32bb-32c7-477a-980f-06e9cc4e7f40&quot;</programlisting>
    <programlisting>id: Customer.id = &quot;f18e32bb-32c7-477a-980f-06e9cc4e7f40&quot;
all: Customer.name + Customer.email = &quot;John Doe^john.doe@mail.com&quot;</programlisting>
    <para>Let’s assume our search string is &quot;john&quot;:<itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>First, the search is performed in <code>all</code> fields of both documents. The system will find the  <code>Customer</code> entity and will include it in search results.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Then, the system will search for the identifier of the previously found customer in the  <code>links</code> fields of all documents. The system will find the   <code>Order</code> and will add it to search results as well.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist></para>
  </section>
</chapter>
